<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>VULNIX</title>
    <link>https://theupbeat.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on VULNIX</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2020 18:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://theupbeat.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating and Managing Virtual Machines using Libvirt</title>
      <link>https://theupbeat.github.io/posts/vm_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2020 18:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://theupbeat.github.io/posts/vm_2/</guid>
      <description>As we have seen a little into KVM/QEMU, Libvirt in the previous post, this post will demonstrate how to create, manage and remove virtual machines.
 Note
I use Void Linux as my base operating system (recently hoped from Manjaro), so the commands will be according to it. But most of the packages are some with similar or different names.
 Before installing packages for KVM/QEMU, we need to check for KVM support.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>KVM, QEMU, Libvirt</title>
      <link>https://theupbeat.github.io/posts/vm_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2020 15:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://theupbeat.github.io/posts/vm_1/</guid>
      <description>Introduction I was looking into virtualization in Linux systems. As we know Linux has arsenal of tools in its back-pocket. It did have something up its sleeve KVM, QEMU, Libvirt. And there a lot of other 3rd party options like VMWare, VirtulBox to name some.
Its interesting that KVM is a kernel module in the Linux system, which helps in getting native-like performance in the virtual machine. So we will be looking into tweaking KVM, QEMU, Libvirt to our convenience and usage.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Browser Configuration</title>
      <link>https://theupbeat.github.io/posts/browser_conf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 16:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://theupbeat.github.io/posts/browser_conf/</guid>
      <description>A Browser is what we use to access the Internet i.e. the World. The technology has advanced to a level that we can mostly access/use everything from our palms. Out of all the software/applications the mostly helpful and useful one is a Browser.
In this post I would like to share my browser configuration and the extensions that I use to make my life a little secure, private and easier.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>control groups (cgroups) - CPUACCT</title>
      <link>https://theupbeat.github.io/posts/cgroups_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2020 18:00:23 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://theupbeat.github.io/posts/cgroups_2/</guid>
      <description>As explained in the previous post, control groups are used to limit, prioritize, etc., the available resources in a system. In this series of post we will be creating, limiting, assigning tasks to the cgroups.
 NOTE
In this whole process I will be using a Arch-based machine with Systemd, specifically Manjaro (please don&amp;rsquo;t come after me).
 Part II - Demonstrating libcgroup We can control the cgroups using shell commands.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://theupbeat.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2020 19:33:42 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://theupbeat.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>My name is TheUpBeat and this site is where I will be posting my thoughts, notes, and tutorials as I learn it myself, about different technical concepts which involves Open Source, Linux, System Administration, Security, etc.
Please excuse me (or) forgive me if there are any shortcomings or mistakes in the website. I write the posts as I learn, so if there is any problem or any mistake in the website, ping me up @: TheUpBeat@protonmail.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>control groups (cgroups) - Introduction</title>
      <link>https://theupbeat.github.io/posts/cgroups_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2020 10:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://theupbeat.github.io/posts/cgroups_1/</guid>
      <description>The Linux Kernel is full of mysteries and tools which can help boost the performance, improve the efficiency and at the same time break the system. This series mainly focuses on the &amp;ldquo;cgroups&amp;rdquo; feature in the Linux Kernel. There will be a series of posts explaining, demonstrating, and tweaking it.
Part I - Introduction What is cgroups cgroups is a feature available to the end user which is present in Linux Kernel.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>